Guide to the William J. Baumol Papers, circa 1940-1995 (bulk 1950-1990)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William J. Baumol Papers circa 1940-1995 (bulk 1950-1990)
Baumol, William J.
70.7 linear feet Extent: 54,675 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00092
Language: Materials in English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of William J. Baumol, noted Princeton and New York University economist, were received as a gift to the Special Collections Library in 1995 and 2001.
Biographical Note
1922, February 26 Born in New York, N.Y.
1936-1938 Attended first formal art classes sponsored by the Works Progress Administration.
1942 BSS, College of the City of New York; organized extracurricular classes on microeconomics.
1942-1943 and 1946 Junior Economist, U.S. Department of Agriculture.
1943-1945 Served in U.S. Army, stationed in France.
1946-1949 London School of Economics; Graduate Student and Assistant Lecturer in American Economy and Economic Dynamics. (Lecture notes for the latter formed the basis for his first published book, Economic Dynamics, 1951, 1959, 1970).
1949 Completed University of London Ph. D. thesis, later published as Welfare Economics and the Theory of the State, 1952, 1965. Ph.D. examiners were Marcus Flemming and Lord Lionel Robbins.
1949-1953 Associate Professor of Economics, Princeton University.
1954-1992 Professor of Economics, Princeton University.
1959 Publication of Business Behavior, Value and Growth (second edition 1966).
1961 Publication of Economic Theory and Operations Analysis (later editions in 1965, 1972, 1976).
1962-1970 Chairman, Committee on the Economic Status of the Profession, American Association of University Professors.
1966 Publication with W.G. Bowen of Performing Arts: The Economic Dilemma.
1967-1975 Past Chairman and member, Economic Policy Council, State of New Jersey.
1968-1970 Vice-President, American Association of University Professors.
1971-current Professor of Economics and Director, C.V. Starr Center for Applied Economics, New York University.
1975 Publication with W.E. Oates of The Theory of Environmental Policy, (second edition 1988).
1978 President, Eastern Economics Association.
1978-1979 President, Association of Environmental and Resource Economists.
1979 Publication with A.S. Blinder of the first edition of introductory textbook, Economics: Principles and Policies. Later editions in 1982, 1985, 1987, 1991, 1994, and 1998.
1981 President, American Economics Association.
1982 Publication with J.C. Panzar and R.D. Willig of Contestable Markets and the Theory of Industry Structure (second edition 1982).
1984 Editor with wife, Hilda Baumol, of Inflation and the Performing Arts.
1986 Publication of Superfairness: Applications and Theory.
1992-current Senior Research Economist and Professor Emeritus of Economics, Princeton University.
Collection Overview
The professional papers of William Baumol are representative of his career as an academic economist and consultant to industry and government. The collection dates from his appointment to the Department of Economics, Princeton University in 1949 until his retirement in 1992 and covers nearly all of his research interests. Some earlier material (1940s) includes notebooks from the London School of Economics (LSE) and papers prepared for the U.S. Department of Agriculture. The bulk of the collection dates from 1950 to 1970 and 1975 to 1990. Materials take the form of correspondence with other economists concerning publications or works in progress; manuscript drafts and galleys; papers prepared for conferences and special lectures; research materials (including notes, materials produced by others, data and other statistical output); special project reports, including grant proposals; teaching materials (lecture notes, exams, course syllabi); material relating to industry consulting work, legal testimony and some printed material.
The contents of the collection display Baumol's diverse interests as an economist. Early material is concerned mainly with dynamic systems and their mathematical expression as well as welfare economics and externalities. His work (with his undergraduate student and future Nobel Prize winner, G.S. Becker) on Classical Monetary Theory is also represented. The outcome of Baumol's role as consultant to industry (in connection with the firms Alderson and Sessions, Mathematica, and Consultants in Industry Economics) is manifest in his work on the behavior of firms and industry structure. Reports prepared for Alderson and Sessions, Mathematica, and Consultants in Industry Economics, as well as drafts of papers relating the business activities of firms to economic theory, including his work on the "sales maximization hypothesis," are contained within the collection.
Other subjects include fairness theory, environmental economics, and the development of his "cost disease model" and "unbalanced growth model" which attempt to explain the fiscal problems of the performing arts, educational systems, etc. Much of his work on the finances of the performing arts was undertaken with his wife, Hilda Baumol. In addition, the collection contains material related to his professional involvement with the American Economic Association, the Eastern Economic Association, the Association of Environmental and Resource Economists, and the American Association of University Professors. The collection also contains legal testimony and reports prepared as an expert witness in antitrust cases before the Federal Communications Commission, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, the Interstate Commerce Commission, among many others.
Correspondents and chief protagonists during Baumol's long career represent many notable economists, including colleagues from the London School of Economics and other English economists, David Finch, Frank Hahn, Jan de van Graaf, Friederich Hayek, Sir John Hicks, Nicholas Kaldor, James Meade, Dennis H. Robertson, Lord Lionel Robbins, and Ralph Turvey; Nobel prize winners G.S. Becker, Milton Friedman, and Paul Samuelson; other prominent twentieth century economists including Robert Dorfman and Don Patinkin; Princeton colleagues Jacob Viner and Harvey Leibenstein; frequent co-authors Elizabeth Bailey and Dietrich Fischer; in addition to former students, Samuel Hollander and Richard Quandt. Also represented are industry leaders from telecommunications, transportation, and public utility sectors. Researchers should note the possibility of cross-referencing with other collections included in the Economists' Papers Project, for example, with the Don Patinkin Papers on the subject of Classical Monetary Theory.
The collection is organized into four series, some of which are further divided into associated subseries: Correspondence, Writings, Subject Files, and Legal Testimony.
The Correspondence Series includes the subseries Correspondence Alphabetical, Correspondence by Subject, and Correspondence by Date. Researchers should note that in addition to letters, other material such as drafts of papers sent to Baumol, clippings, and book reviews are included within the series. The material in the Correspondence Alphabetical Subseries covers the early part of Baumol's career, 1943-1968, with the bulk of it dating from the 1950s. Topics covered are representative of his early research interests or those of his correspondents, who for the most part were British colleagues from Baumol's graduate studies at the LSE. The researcher will find that this series is a likely source for viewing the development and formulation of Baumol's ideas as well as his comments on the theories of others. The most substantive correspondence (with more than twenty letters exchanged for each) is between Gary Becker, Robert Dorfman, David Finch, Jan de v. Graaf, Frank Hahn, Don Patinkin, and Paul Samuelson. Much of the correspondence contains copies of both letters to and from Baumol, although there are exceptions to this, particularly for the earlier letters. The last two subseries, Correspondence by Subject and Correspondence by Date, overlap somewhat in terms of the period covered (1952-1984 for the first, and 1974-1990 for the second). The Correspondence by Subject Subseries deals mostly with Baumol's professional activities with the American Economic Association and his other professional activities, including tenure reviews and other recommendations, with notable exceptions in correspondence files for Areeda-Turner (on predatory pricing), Samuelson-Dorfman (on Marx), and Hollander (on Classical economics). Because of the sensitive nature of some materials in the Subject Subseries, researchers using them must sign a release form provided by Research Services staff. The Correspondence by Date Subseries covers a variety of topics but deals mostly with requests for papers or with the details of various engagements.
The Writings Series includes drafts, galley proofs, handwritten notes, correspondence relating to publisher's contracts, and final versions of many of Baumol's published writings, as well as some unpublished and working papers. While the collection does not contain a complete set of Baumol's hundreds of publications, the Writings Series is representative of his diverse research interests and his prolific writing ability. In an effort to preserve the original organization of the Baumol papers, this series is chronological as opposed to organized by subject. Hence, the researcher interested in constructing the process of Baumol's contributions to the theory of, say, Industry Structure, would be advised to consult the Subject Series for teaching materials or research files and the Correspondence Series for a more complete picture.
The Subject Files Series is organized into the following subseries: Project Files, Teaching Materials, and Research Files. The Project Files Subseries is arranged by subject and includes reports prepared for industry consulting to firms such as Southern Railways (1963-65), General Foods (1963) and Morgan Stanley (1963-64); projects on Fairness, Scale Economies, and the Performing Arts; and testimony prepared for government Senate and House of Representatives subcommittees. The bulk of the material is from 1975-1985. The Teaching Material Subseries includes four undated notebooks from Baumol's student days, lecture notes on Dynamics and Welfare Theory (the notes which formed the basis for his first published book and his Ph.D. thesis) and a copy of Lord Robbins' lecture on Classical Economics. The Research Files Subseries is organized by subject: History of Economics, Industrial Organization, Fairness, Productivity/Entrepreneurship, and General.
The Legal Testimony Series contains voluminous records of legal proceedings in which Baumol played a key role as a consultant or witness. The series is organized by the regulatory or legal body involved in legal proceedings: Civil Actions Subseries, Federal Communications Commission Subseries, Federal Energy Regulatory Commission Subseries, Federal Trade Commission Subseries, Interstate Commerce Commission Subseries, Public Utilities Subseries, Tax Court Subseries, and Miscellaneous. The material within each subseries is arranged chronologically. There are restricted materials in this series. Some of the materials are clearly marked as attorney-client privileged information (where the client is a major firm) or sealed by the court in question. It is impossible, without going through every item, to ensure an exhaustive list of material that might compromise certain industry secrets or other privileged information; therefore, the researcher using this series must sign a release form provided by the reference staff.
PROCESSING NOTE: The materials received by Duke University arrived from Professor Baumol's offices at Princeton, New York University, and from his private residence. These were treated as one single accession and the materials from all three shipments have been consolidated. Hence, while the original organization has been mostly preserved at the folder level, at the box level this is not the case. Wherever possible the original folder labels were used in organizing the collection. Notable exceptions to this are the material in the Legal Testimony Series and the performing arts, government projects, and industry consulting folders in the Subject Files Series as the bulk of this material was received loose.
The addition to the collection (2001-0169)(11,825 items, 19.20 linear feet, dated 1964-1995 and undated) contains professional papers including correspondence, reviews, consulting files, lecture notes, drafts of writings, grant files, and three black-and-white transparencies. Revisions of Baumol's writings on productivity and his books Economics: Principles and Policy and Productivity and American Leadership: The Long View are represented among the drafts.
The addition to the collection (2001-0170)(2000 items, 5 linear feet, dated 1974-1990) holds files containing or regarding reviews, recommendations, proposals, engagements, and other correspondence. Subjects include the World Resources Institute, the Eastern Economic Association, and the manuscript of On Finances of the Performing Arts during Stagflation. There are also 114 floppy disks of graphs and texts for writings by Baumol as well as one reel-to-reel audiotape.
[Original audiovisual materials and original electronic media are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact a reference archivist before coming to use this collection.]
Subject Headings
Baumol, William J.; Baumol, Hilda, 1923-; Hahn, Frank; Graaff, J. de V.; Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-; Hicks, John Richard, Sir, 1904-; Kaldor, Nicholas, 1908-1986; Meade, J. E. (James Edward), 1907-; Robertson, Dennis Holme, Sir, 1890-1963; Robbins, Lionel Robbins, Baron, 1898-1984; Turvey, Ralph; Becker, Gary Stanley, 1930-; Friedman, Milton, 1912-; Samuelson, Paul Anthony, 1915-; Dorfman, Robert; Patinkin, Don; Viner, Jacob, 1892-1970; Leibenstein, Harvey; United States. Federal Communications Commission; United States. Federal Energy Regulatory Commission; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Electric utilities-Rates; Railroad companies-Rates; Economics, Mathematical; Welfare economics; Monetary policy; Antitrust investigations-United States; Labor economics; Statics and dynamics (Social sciences); Industrial productivity; Performing arts-Finance; Performing arts-United States-Finance; Distributive justice; Entrepreneurship; Environmental economics; Public utilities-United States-Law and legislation; Telephone companies-Rates; Education-Finance; Environmental policy -- Economic aspects; Machine-readable records; Audiotapes
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1943-1990
  Material within each folder is not in date order. Includes both to and from correspondence except for some of the earlier correspondence and where noted below. Also includes drafts of papers, book reviews, clippings and other materials sent to Baumol. All folder titles are the original titles. Some Correspondence By Subject Subseries materials are restricted: they are open to research, but patrons must sign a release form before using them.
  - Alphabetical Subseries 1943-1968 (bulk 1950s)
    The names listed below indicate that several substantive letters were exchanged.
    - A ( 1949-1963): Includes Maurice Allais, G.C. Archibald (with R.G. Lipsey), Wroe Alderson (Box C1)
    - B ( 1950-1966): Includes Karl Brunner and Hans Brems (Box C1)
    - Becker, G.S. ( 1951-1959): Correspondence exchanged while Becker was a graduate student at The University of Chicago (Box C1)
    - C-D-E ( 1948-1966): Includes Les Chandler, Robert Dorfman, Harold Demsetz (Box C1)
    - F ( ca. 1950-1960): Includes David Finch, Milton Friedman, C.E. Ferguson, and Richard Foote (of the US Dept. of Agriculture) (Box C1)
    - G ( 1948-1967): Includes Jan de v. Graaf (letters from, not to) and John Kenneth Galbraith (Box C1)
    - H ( 1947-1967): Includes Sir J.R. Hicks, Ursula Hicks, R.F. Harrod, Terence Hutchinson (Box C1)
    - Hahn, Frank ( undated ca. 1948-1958) letters from, not to (Box C1)
    - J-K ( 1959-1968): Includes Nicholas Kaldor, Harold Kuhn (Box C1)
    - L ( 1951-1968): Includes Ian Little, Friedrich Lutz, Harvey Leibenstein (Box C1)
    - M ( 1949-1966): Includes James Meade, Jacob Marschak (Box C1)
    - N-O ( 1948-1966) (Box C1)
    - P ( 1952-1967): Includes Allen Peacock, M. Peston (Box C1)
    - Patinkin, Don ( 1953-1961) (Box C1)
    - R ( 1946-1966): Includes Lord Lionel Robbins, D.H. Robertson, Joan Robinson (Box C1)
    - S ( 1943-1963): Includes George Shackle, Robert Strotz, George Stigler, Paul Samuelson, and letters written while serving in the Army to Stuart Siebert (Box C1)
    - T ( 1949-1965): Includes J. Tinbergen, S.C. Tsiang (Box C1)
    - Turvey, Ralph ( 1951-1969) (Box C1)
    - V ( 1954-1966): Includes Jacob Viner (Box C1)
    - W ( 1951-1965) (Box C1)
  - Correspondence by Subject Subseries 1952-1984 (bulk 1975-1982): RESTRICTED
    Material is not in date order.
    - American Association of University Professors ( 1965) (Box C1)
    - American Economic Association (AEA): Adam Smith Session ( 1977) (Box C1)
    - AEA: China Exchange Committee ( 1980) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Committee on Political Discrimination ( 1978) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Encyclopedia Committee ( 1980) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Environment Session ( 1976) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Meetings ( 1976-1977) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Meetings ( 1979-1984) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Meetings ( 1982) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Nominating Committee ( 1983-1984) (Box C1)
    - AEA: Presidential Address ( 1981-1982) (Box C1)
    - American Economic Review ( 1975-1984) (Box C1)
    - American Stock Exchange ( 1977) (Box C1)
    - Areeda-Turner ( 1978-1984) (Box C2)
    - Association of Environmental and Resource Economists (AERE) ( 1977-1984) (Box C2)
    - AERE Newsletter ( 1981-1982) (Box C2)
    - Association of American Railroads ( 1963) (Box C2)
    - Crank Letters ( 1964-1982) (Box C2)
    - Eastern Economic Association ( 1977-1978) (Box C2)
    - Environmental Economics ( 1973-1974) (Box C2)
    - Hollander, Samuel ( 1979-1986) (Box C2)
    - Institute for Defense Analyses ( 1964) (Box C2)
    - Intermountain Economic Review ( 1977) (Box C2)
    - International Research and Exchanges Board ( 1983) (Box C2)
    - Interschool Humanities Council ( 1976) (Box C2)
    - Journal of Economic Literature ( 1975) (Box C2)
    - Journal of Environmental Economics and Management ( 1976) (Box C2)
    - Journal Referee Reports ( 1975-1983) (Box C2)
    - Leontief Award ( 1978) (Box C2)
    - McCarter Theatre ( 1979-1980) (Box C2)
    - National Science Foundation (NSF) Amendment ( 1981) (Box C2)
    - NSF Proposal Referee Reports ( 1975-1981) (Box C2)
    - New York University ( 1977-1979) (Box C2)
    - Princeton University ( 1952-1969) (Box C2)
    - Publishers' Contracts ( 1960-1977) (Box C2)
    - Samuelson-Dorfman ( 1973-1983) (Box C2)
    - Tenure and Promotions ( 1977-1983) (Box C2)
  - Correspondence by Date Subseries 1975-1990
    - 1975-1981 (7 folders) (Box C2)
    - 1981 (Box C3)
    - 1981-1982: Engagements (Box C3)
    - 1982 (Box C3)
    - 1983 (Box C3)
    - 1983: Engagements (Box C3)
    - 1984 (Box C3)
    - 1984: Engagements (Box C3)
    - 1984: Engagements Declined (Box C3)
    - 1986-1990 (Box C3)
- Writings Series, 1947-1995
  Includes notes, drafts, correspondence and comments of others, final versions, publisher's contracts, and reviews. Folder titles and dates refer to the publication in question. Arranged chronologically.
  - ca. 1947-1961 (Box W1)
    - Early Papers (Box W1)
    - Misc. proofs and offprints ( 1947-1957) (Box W1)
    - Book Reviews ( 1947-1956) (Box W1)
    - Economic Dynamics ( 1951) (Box W1)
    - The Von-Neumann--Morgenstern Utility Index ( 1951) (2 folders) (Box W1)
    - Classical Monetary Theory: The Outcome of the Discussion ( 1952) (Box W1)
    - The Transactions Demand for Cash ( 1952) (Box W1)
    - Welfare Economics and the Theory of the State ( 1952) (Box W1)
    - Recent Developments in Mathematical Economics ( 1953) (Box W1)
    - The Ricardo Effect in the Point-Input-Point-Output Case ( 1953) (Box W1)
    - Firms with Limited Money Capital ( 1953) (Box W1)
    - Bernoulli Translation ( 1954) (Box W1)
    - Economic Processes and Policies ( 1954) (Box W1)
    - More on the Multiplier Effects of a Balanced Budget ( 1956) (Box W1)
    - Magnification ( 1956) (Box W1)
    - Decision Making under Uncertainty ( 1957) (Box W1)
    - Speculation, Profitability, and Stability ( 1958) (Box W1)
    - Cardinal Utility which is Ordinal ( 1958) (Box W1)
    - Topology of Second Order Linear Difference Equations with Constant Coefficients ( 1958) (Box W1)
    - Activity Analysis in One Lesson ( 1958) (Box W1)
    - Alternative Interest Theories in Disequilibrium Conditions ( 1959) (Box W1)
    - Business Behavior, Value and Growth ( 1959) (2 folders) (Box W1)
    - Mathematical Models and Thinking in Marketing ( 1960) (Box W1)
    - Wine Pricing, Capital Theory and Practice ( 1960) (Box W1)
    - Economic Theory and Operations Analysis ( 1961) (Box W1)
    - Pitfalls in Contracyclical Policies ( 1961) (Box W1)
    - What Price Economic Growth? ( 1961) (Box W1)
  - 1962-1976 (Box W2)
    - Stocks, Flows and Monetary Theory ( 1962) (Box W2)
    - Urban Services ( 1962) (Box W2)
    - Theory of the Expansion of the Firm ( 1962) (Box W2)
    - On Dividend Policy and Market Imperfections ( 1963) (Box W2)
    - Decomposition Pricing for Decentralization ( 1964) (Box W2)
    - Dynamics and Statics in Economics ( 1964) (Box W2)
    - Rules of Thumb ( 1964) (Box W2)
    - On the Geometry of Second Best ( 1965) (Box W2)
    - The Stock Market and Economic Efficiency ( 1965) (Box W2)
    - Models of Economic Competition ( 1965) (Box W2)
    - Incremental Costs, Pricing and the Differential ( 1966) (Box W2)
    - Economics ( 1967) (Box W2)
    - Macroeconomics of Unbalanced Growth ( 1967) (Box W2)
    - Error Produced by Linearization ( 1967) (Box W2)
    - On the Appropriate Discount Rate ( 1967) (Box W2)
    - Public Expenditure Decisions ( 1968) (Box W2)
    - Precursors in Mathematical Economics ( 1968) (2 folders) (Box W2)
    - Regulation of Public Utility Profits ( 1969) (Box W2)
    - Transportation and the City ( 1970) (Box W2)
    - Sir John Hicks ( 1970) (Box W2)
    - Models of Oligopolistic Competition ( 1970) (Box W2)
    - Optimal Departures from Marginal Cost Pricing ( 1970) (Box W2)
    - External Economies and Second Order Conditions ( 1970) (Box W2)
    - On The Behavioral Theory of the Firm ( 1971) (Box W2)
    - Say's at Least Eight Laws ( 1975) (Box W2)
    - Leningrad Paper ( 1975) (Box W2)
    - Marx Papers ( 1975) (Box W2)
    - Various Papers ( 1975) (Box W2)
    - Cost Minimizing Number of Firms ( 1976) (Box W2)
    - Various Papers ( 1976) (Box W2)
  - 1977-1980 (Box W3)
    - Cost Minimizing Number of Firms ( 1977) (Box W3)
    - Various Papers ( 1977) (Box W3)
    - Output Distribution Frontier ( 1978) (Box W3)
    - Business Morality and the Social Interest ( 1978) (Box W3)
    - Quasi-Optimality: The Price We Must Pay for a Price System ( 1978) (Box W3)
    - Various Papers ( 1978) (Box W3)